The Death of a City: Elegy for Sarajevo -- A special report.; A People Under Artillery Fire Manage to Retain Humanity

By JOHN F. BURNS,

Published: June 8, 1992

SARAJEVO, Bosnia and Herzegovina, June 7— As the 155-millimeter howitzer shells whistled down on this crumbling city today, exploding thunderously into buildings all around, a disheveled, stubble-bearded man in formal evening attire unfolded a plastic chair in the middle of Vase Miskina Street. He lifted his cello from its case and began playing Albinoni's Adagio.

There were only two people to hear him, and both fled, dodging from doorway to doorway, before the performance ended.

Each day at 4 P.M., the cellist, Vedran Smailovic, walks to the same spot on the pedestrian mall for a concert in honor of Sarajevo's dead.

The spot he has chosen is outside the bakery where several high-explosive rounds struck a bread line 12 days ago, killing 22 people and wounding more than 100. If he holds to his plan, there will be 22 performances before his gesture has run its course.

Two months into a civil war that turns more murderous by the day, Sarajevo, the capital of Bosnia and Herzegovina, is a skeleton of the thriving, accomplished city it was. It is a wasteland of blasted mosques, churches and museums; of fire-gutted office towers, hotels and sports stadiums, and of hospitals, music schools and libraries punctured by rockets, mortars and artillery shells.

Parks have been pressed into service as emergency cemeteries, and the pathetic lines of graves march ever farther up the hillsides toward the gun emplacements.

What is happening here, in a European city that escaped two World Wars with only minor damage, is hard to grasp for many of those enduring it.

It is a disaster of such magnitude, and of such seeming disconnectedness from any achievable military or political goals, that those who take shelter for days in basement bunkers, emerging briefly into daylight for fresh supplies of bread and water, exhaust themselves trying to make sense of it.

Many, like Mr. Smailovic, who played the cello for the Sarajevo Opera, reach for an anchor amid the chaos by doing something, however small, that carries them back to the stable, reasoned life they led before.

Mr. Smailovic, 36 years old, spoke over the blasts of the shells that have poured down on the city unremittingly for the last 48 hours. The barrages by the Serbian forces seem to be a paroxysm of fury at their failure to capture the city after weeks of dumping thousands of tons of high explosives from the hillsides.

He could have been speaking for all the survivors trapped here, in defiance of the Serbian nationalists' insistence that only the ethnic partitioning of the city, and of the republic, can bring them security.

"My mother is a Muslim and my father is a Muslim," Mr. Smailovic said, "but I don't care. I am a Sarajevan, I am a cosmopolitan, I am a pacifist." Then he added: "I am nothing special, I am a musician, I am part of the town. Like everyone else, I do what I can."

In Sarajevo, as in many cities, towns and villages across this former Yugoslav republic, Serbs, Muslims and Croats, the third major ethnic group in the population of 4.4 million, have lived for centuries side by side, so much so that their cultures, families and life styles have grown into each other -- creating a society of striking depth and variety. Symbol of Civility Now Symbol of Pain

They have done so in a landscape that is one of the most beautiful in Europe, a place of Alpine mountains and blue-green rivers, of terra cotta-roofed houses that cling to precipitous hillsides, of white stone mosques with green copper domes and pencil-slim minarets.

Sarajevo, in a narrow valley bordered on all sides by mountains, has long been the symbol of this richly textured life, enchanting generations of travelers since the present city was established by a Turkish sultan in 1462.

Now it is a symbol of another kind -- of a place where Muslims, Serbs, Croats, and other religious and ethnic minorities, including Albanians and a tiny population of Jews, suffer together. They endure the gunfire of Serbian nationalists who believe that the independent nation of Bosnia and Herzegovina proclaimed on March 2, and led by Muslims and Croats, will dominate and eventually persecute Serbs.

From this conviction -- met with increasing ferocity in many parts of the republic by Muslims and Croats, some of whom have adopted tactics as brutal as those of the Serbs -- has grown the war that is draining the life from Sarajevo.

The conflict here had small beginnings early in April, when decisions by the European Community and the United States to recognize the new nation led to barricades being thrown up around the city by rival ethnic militias.

Early in May, it got out of control after Alija Izetbegovic, the Muslim who is President of the new republic, was kidnapped by the Serbian forces, and Muslim and Croatian troops retaliated by ambushing a convoy of the Serbian-led Yugoslav Army as it evacuated an army headquarters in the city.

The President, who was released in exchange for guarantees of safe passage for the convoy, was out on Marshal Tito Street in the center of Sarajevo this afternoon. He walked gingerly around piles of broken glass and rubble from the shattered facades of apartment buildings built during the time before World War I when Sarajevo was an outpost of the Austro-Hungarian Empire.

The 67-year-old leader, a lawyer and economist who spent nearly 10 years in prison under Yugoslavia's Communist rulers for his writings on Muslim beliefs, sought to reassure scattered groups of people he met along the way. But he made no effort to hide his own anxiety after weeks of heavy shelling.

"Are you scared?" he asked a group of militiamen standing guard with Kalashnikov automatic rifles under an archway leading into the Solomon Palace, a six-story apartment building that was once home to some of the city's leading Jews, many of whom died in the Nazi terror.

"A little," one militiaman replied, shifting nervously in a denim jacket embroidered with the fleur-de-lis badge that is the emblem of the new republic.

"I am afraid too," replied Mr. Izetbegovic, who has spent long periods in a basement bunker in a nearby Government building. "But we must hold out."

For many here, that has become a prospect of appalling bleakness. Although the United Nations on Friday reached the outline of an agreement to take control of Butmir Airport, on the city's outskirts, from the Serbian forces and to open a corridor into town, there is little confidence here that the Serbs will carry it out.

By lifting the siege, the Serbs would effectively acknowledge that they have lost the city, many in Saravejo believe. Already, all but a few of Sarajevo's suburbs are controlled by Bosnian territorial forces made up of Muslims, Serbs and Croats.

But if relief supplies do not arrive soon, desperation may turn to catastrophe. Only a handful of Government services still operate, and those in skeletal state. No one seems to know how many people remain, but it appears to be at least half the city's prewar population of 560,000 -- possibly many more. Food and Hope Are Running Low

The Serbian nationalist forces allow no food to pass through their roadblocks on the periphery of town, and supplies that have been sneaked past their gun positions on the hills have been minimal. Most families have only loaves of bread baked by the single bakery that continues to function, using reserve supplies of flour from silos that are in a part of town under Mr. Izetbegovic's control.

To this, some families have added a thin gruel made of water and nettles taken from the lower slopes of the surrounding hills. With inventive cooking, and private supplies of flour, Sarajevans produce the likes of French bread and a sugared Turkish cake called kevlici.

But no one outside the Government knows how long the flour supplies might hold out, and fear of starvation is widespread. When two Western reporters entered the city on Friday, one of the first people they encountered was a professor of biophysics from the medical faculty of Sarajevo University, Dr. Hamid Pasic.

"I am hungry!" he said. "I am 76 years old, I am a professor, and I am hungry!"

Those who venture out for food do so at great risk. Although some of the gunnery appears to be aimed at military targets, most of the rounds land in densely populated parts of the city. The sections of town taking the worst punishment include the central district and Bascarsija, an old quarter of mosques, narrow alleyways and wooden-front workshops and boutiques.

The toll has risen rapidly, particularly this weekend, when the Serbian gunners began their most merciless barrage. Every minute or two, with only a few pauses, shells slammed into apartment buildings and the remnants of commercial districts, each volley hitting with a blast that could be heard miles away.

At night, the skyline was a facsimile of Baghdad during the gulf war -- with gunners' flares lighting the high-rises of the city center in silhouette, and tracer fire skipping across the sky.

From a vantage point in the old town, fires blazed at every point of the compass, some of them huge conflagrations that burned for hours. Wisdom and Tears Of a Barkeeper

The number of dead and wounded was another unknown, but gravediggers were hard pressed to keep up with the new bodies arriving by the hour.

At Kovlaci Park above Bascarsija, 185 new graves, each with a coffin-shaped wooden marker bearing the Muslim emblems of a star and a crescent moon, lay row upon row on the hillside. The graves were piles of freshly turned earth beneath clusters of wild roses, carnations and violets.

Shells hitting the hillside drove a steam-shovel operator who was digging the graves into the cover of a ridge abutment. While he took shelter there, two middle-aged women carrying plastic bags of bread were hit by a new blast. Both were killed.

For Kemal Aljevic, the 45-year-old owner of a bar in Bascarsija called Alf, after the American television puppet character, the sight of the Kovlaci graves was too much. With tears streaming down his cheeks, Mr. Aljevic said that the Serbian gunners appeared to be repeating the destruction of Vukovar, the Croatian town of 45,000 that was reduced to rubble by artillery fire last year.

"This will be three times worse than Vukovar," he said.

As in Vukovar, the Serbs seem to use the heaviest weapons of the Yugoslav Army, which formally withdrew from Bosnia and Herzegovina three weeks ago and turned at least 55,000 men over to a new force of Bosnia's ethnic Serbs.

One of two Sarajevo newspapers still being produced, Oslobodenje, quoted Yugoslav Army officers who had defected to the Bosnians as saying that weapons being used in the barrage included 155-millimeter howitzers, 120-millimeter mortars, 104-millimeter tank cannon and 132-millimeter multiple-rocket launchers. The paper said a total of 4,000 tons of high explosives had been fired into the city.

Some of the artillery shells are coming from a former Yugoslav Army barracks at Hampjesic, 20 miles east of Sarajevo, the officers reportedly added. Houses of Worship Become Targets

The destruction has reached every quarter of Sarajevo, and almost every landmark. Fifty of the city's 80 mosques have been damaged or destroyed, including the oldest in the Balkans, Tabacki Mesdid, which dates to 1450. The Morica Han, a 15th-century Turkish inn stop for caravans, and the Islamic Theological Faculty, also from the 15th century, were damaged.

The main synagogue and the Roman Catholic cathedral have been hit, though only lightly damaged. The main broadcasting center and its transmitter have been repeatedly shelled; repairs at feverish speed have kept the radio and television stations on the air.

The Serbian nationalists seem to have taken little care to avoid buildings of historic importance to the ethnic Serbs who live here, 38 percent of the city's population before the fighting.

One building was extensively damaged by a shell that pierced its glass dome. It was the National Library, formerly the city hall, where in 1914, Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria-Hungary attended a reception minutes before he and his wife, Sophie, were assassinated by a 19-year-old Serbian nationalist, Gavrilo Princip. Half a mile away, at the site of the assassination, the museum dedicated to Mr. Princip has now been destroyed.

The main Serbian Orthodox church in the city center has also been extensively damaged.

Sites linked to the 1984 Olympics have come under fire, too. Both cupolas have been destroyed atop the former United States Consulate building, a neo-classical structure on a rise above the city center, which served as the Olympic museum. Its roof was penetrated by a shell, and all its windows were shattered.

The hospitals are packed with the wounded, many with amputated limbs from shrapnel blasts. Doctors report an unusually high incidence of heart attacks and of psychological distress.

With gasoline unavailable, many of the doctors walk miles to work through streets where every intersection offers clear sightlines to snipers in the hills. Along the way, hundreds of cars, buses and trams lie destroyed, many of them burned-out hulks.

A lung specialist who walks back from the Vrazova Health Center every day spends her nights in a shopping-center storage room in the city's old quarter with her husband, a cardiologist.

With them, on mattresses on the floor, are a taxi driver, dentist, fireman, electrical engineer, waiter and computer scientist, together with their families -- a cross-section of Sarajevo life, pressed together as they rarely were before the fighting. Amid occasional tears, there are moments of joy over chess games, crossword puzzles and surprise meetings with old friends from other parts of town.

"You're alive!" a professor exclaimed to another who appeared in a shopping arcade on Saturday night, hugging him tightly for a full minute as both wept.

On a radio broadcast that was frequently drowned out by exploding shells, an announcer urged people to turn up the volume on the station's Bosnian patriotic songs and Beatles music. "We cannot kill these maniacs with guns," he said, "so let's kill them with love and music." Escape Mechanisms: Music and Disbelief

In an apartment nearby, with only a candle burning to deny the gunners a target, the 16-year-old daughter of a Muslim electrical engineer and his architect wife, Meliha Dzirlo, lingered at a piano into the small hours playing Beethoven's "Pathetique" Sonata and a polonaise by Chopin.

Everywhere, when they were not arranging forays for food or water or exchanging names of those killed or wounded, people appealed for help from the outside world. After listening to a shortwave-radio account of the United Nations plans for relief convoys, Asim Hadzic, a 30-year-old Muslim who is a food-company salesman, shook his head.

"It would be a good start but it isn't enough," he said. "We want military intervention."

The doctor who walks every day to the Vrazova Clinic, a Muslim who, fearing for her house, asked not to be identified, took a wider view.

"I can't believe this is all real," she said, gesturing toward a pile of rubble from an apartment building. "Here we are on the eve of the 21st century -- in Europe, in a beautiful city and a country that offered people every possibility of a good life. How can such a thing happen? And how can a so-called civilized world allow it to continue?"

Photos: A man reflecting at a grave yesterday in a newly reopened cemetery in Sarajevo, the capital of Bosnia and Herzegovina. Many ethnic groups use the Serbian cemetery because it is considered the safest in the city. (pg. A1); After a night of heavy shelling, smoke and flames rise from the tallest building in Sarajevo, the capital of Bosnia and Herzegovina. (pg. A6) (Agence France-Presse) Map of Yugoslavia showing location of Sarajevo. (pg. A6)